Guide to the Papers of the Women's National Indian Association, 1880-1951.
Papers of the Women's National Indian Association
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of the Women's National Indian Association 1880-1951.
9237
Women's National Indian Association (U.S.)
1.2 cubic ft
Correspondence, Financial Records, Legal Documents, Manuscripts, Photographs, Printed Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Minutes, correspondence, legal documents, and a small number of photographs documenting the work of the Association.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Organization founded by Mary Lucinda Bonney and Amelia Stone Quinton in 1879. Initially named the Central Indian Committee, and then the Indian Treaty-Keeping and Protective Association (1881-1882), it worked to prevent white settlers from encroaching on American Indian lands. A reform organization advocating Christianization and assimilation of American Indians, it was instrumental in the passage of the General Allotment Act of 1887. Led throughout most of its influential years by the indefatigable Amelia Stone Quinton, the Association in its heyday had 60 branch organizations in 27 states. Known for its ability to influence Indian policy on a national level, the organization also supported Christian missions on reservations throughout the country. Its name changed to Women's National Indian Association in 1882, and its efforts came to focus largely on Christian missionary work among the Indians and efforts to promote their assimilation into white society. The organization changed its name to National Indian Association in 1901. While the organization must have generated a mountain of correspondence in its 72 years of existence, very little is found among the papers.It dissolved itself in 1951.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Minutes, correspondence, legal documents, and a small number of photographs documenting the work of the Association. Minutes of the Indian Treaty-Keeping and Protective Association, 1880-1883, including its constitution and financial reports; minutes of the trustees, the Executive Board, and the members of the Women's National Indian Association and then the National Indian Association, 1880-1951; documents including the organization's charter and certificate of incorporation, and the constitution of the National Indian Association; reports of missions, 1887-1930; the Indian's Friend and other publications; and photographs of Bible schools and other scenes. Also includes the seal of the organization.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Women's National Indian Association (U.S.); Huntington Free Library.; Quinton, Amelia S.; Bonney, Mary Lucinda; Indian Treaty-Keeping and Protective Association.; National Indian Association.; Women's National Indian Association (U.S.)
Subjects:
Social work with Indians.; Indians of North America.; Indians of North America--Societies, etc.; Women--United States--Societies and clubs.; Women missionaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Forms part of the Native American Collection. (NAC)
SERIES LIST
Series I. Meeting minutes and correspondence
Series II. Report of Missions
Series III. Other publications
Series IV. Photographs
Series V. Other items
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Meeting minutes and correspondence
  - 2 handwritten minute books, 1880-1886 (Box 2)
  - Minutes of the Indian Treaty Keeping and Protective Association, December 11, 1880-October 18, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 1
  - Minutes of the Trustees of the Women's National Indian Association, March 11, 1887-November 22, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 55
  - Minutes of the Executive Board and Annual Meetings of the Women's National Indian Association, February 26, 1987-February 11, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 89
  - Minutes of the Executive Board and Annual Meetings of the Women's National Indian Association, November 20, 1890-October 27, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 227
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, December 4, 1913-Deecmber 8, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 1
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, May 26, 1917-December 4, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 64
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, April 15, 1920-December 4, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 136
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, May 6, 1925-December 5, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 223
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, March 27, 1928-December 7, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 280
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, February 20, 1930-December 4, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 332
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, May 3, 1932-December 3, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 397
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, Januar 3, 1935-December 4, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 462
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, January 27, 1937-December 5, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 517
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, May 7, 1939-December 4, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 595
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, January 11, 1943-December 4, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 669
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings, papers of dissolution April 18, 1951; final issue of The Indian's Friend, vol. 53, no. 2, June 1951., April 2, 1948-June 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 727
  - Executive Board and Annual Meetings holographic copies., 1895-1913 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 770
  - Legal documents, A. Charter and Certificate of Incorporation. B. Typed copies of Charter. C. Constitution of National Indian Association. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 1
  - Deed papers, Turtle Mountain Mission, ND (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 31
  - Correspondence, 1907-1920 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 44
  - Correspondence, Publications Committee (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 60
  - Missionary Work of the Women's National Indian Association and Letters of Missionaries, Novembe 17, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 81
- Series II. Report of Missions
  Also available on Reel 3, Frame 94
  - Missions, A. Mission Report, n.d. B. A Chronology, and Data of Our Missions and Their Transfers. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 71
  - Report of Missionary Work, November 1886 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 95
  - Christian Civilization and Missionary Work, November 30, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 113
  - Report on Missionary Work, November 1888 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 121
  - Report of Missionary Department, November 1890 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 129
  - Report of the Missionary Department, November 1891 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 141
  - Our Missions for the year 1895 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 159
  - Our Missionary Report for 1896 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 192
  - Our Missionary Report for 1897 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 222
  - The Report of Missions for 1900 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 257
  - Report of Missions for 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 276
  - Missionary Report for 1903 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 303
  - Missions of 1904 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 326
  - Missions of 1905 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 342
  - Report of Missions, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 358
  - Report of Missions, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 380
  - Report of Missions, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 393
  - Report of Missions, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 411
  - Report of Missions, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 428
  - Report of Missions, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 450
  - Report of Missions, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 467
  - Report of Missions, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 488
- Series III. Other publications
  Also available on Reel 3, Frame 674
  - Annual Meetings of the National Indian Association (3 items), 1911, 1914, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - National Indian Association untitled appeals (3 items) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A Glimpse of Our Missions, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Our Industrial Work by Mrs. N. DeG. Doubleday, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Meeting the Needs, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Problems of Indian Citizenship by Emily S. Cook, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Indian's Appeal: Rocky Boy Mission (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Story of Pah-ah-wut, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A Timely Reminder (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Two Ways to Help the Indians by Mrs. F.N. Doubleday, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Work to Which the Association is Pledged (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - National Indian Association Executive Board, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New Mexico home (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - En Route to Yerington, Nevada (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Oklahoma Photographs (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Natchie Town Bible School (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Evening Shade, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Sycamore Bible School (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Red Bird; organ, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Saturday Afternoon in Vian (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - West View (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Group portrait of the WNIA convention in Washington, D.C. - in a separate, single Folder, December 5-7, 1893 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Series V. Other items
  - Duplicate items (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Haskell Institute YMCA Bulletin, vol. 15, no. 5, January 1925 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 512
  - The Indian's Friend, January 1925 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 520
  - Addresses of the President of the Women's National Indian Association (3 items), 1885, 1886, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 535
  - Annual Meeting and Report, October 27, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 561
  - Reports on Indian Home Building (6 items), 1888-1902 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 575
  - New York City Indian Association, constitution, by-laws, reports (3 items), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 613
  - Sketch of the Washington Auxiliary of the National Indian Association, 1882-1903 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 661
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books - cataloged individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
Ruskins, John. Queen of the Air (belonged to Amelia Stone Quinton)
Rand, McNally & Co. The World's Congress of Representative Women, Volume I and II (belonged to Amelia Stone Quinton)